<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Support staff | Fahim Ahmad</title>
    <link>/tag/support-staff/</link>
      <atom:link href="/tag/support-staff/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Support staff</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© Fahim Ahmad (2020)</copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/media/icon_hua2ec155b4296a9c9791d015323e16eb5_11927_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Support staff</title>
      <link>/tag/support-staff/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mediating the relation between workplace stressors and distress in ID support staff: Comparison between the roles of psychological inflexibility and coping styles</title>
      <link>/publication/kurz-et-al-2014/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/kurz-et-al-2014/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Warning:&lt;/strong&gt; In some regards, I&amp;rsquo;m proud of this paper. It is my first first-authored paper and the first paper for which I was the primary data analyst. Through this project, I got a great introduction to mediation, path analysis, and structural equation modeling. This was also my first experience where someone entrusted me with their data. The paper was accepted in my second year of grad school.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, in the years since then, I&amp;rsquo;ve learned a lot about longitudinal data analysis, multilevel thinking, and the distinction between between- and within-person processes. These studies have led me to conclude that cross-sectional data are a poorly-suited for studying person-level mediation. It&amp;rsquo;s not impossible that the mediational processes discussed and estimated in this paper are reasonable approximations of the day-to-day processes as lived in the lives of our participants and others like them. But it&amp;rsquo;s a stretch and I recommend others take the findings in this paper very lightly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you would like an introduction to the issues I&amp;rsquo;m dancing around, I recommend the (2012) chapter by the great Ellen Hamaker, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.guilford.com/books/Handbook-of-Research-Methods-for-Studying-Daily-Life/Mehl-Conner/9781462513055&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Why researchers should think &amp;ldquo;within-person&amp;rdquo;: A paradigmatic rationale&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. These opinions are mine and mine alone. I do not speak for my co-authors.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
