<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>2 | Fahim Ahmad</title>
    <link>/publication-type/2/</link>
      <atom:link href="/publication-type/2/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>2</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© Fahim Ahmad (2020)</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 22 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/media/icon_hua2ec155b4296a9c9791d015323e16eb5_11927_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>2</title>
      <link>/publication-type/2/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Predicting healthcare-seeking behavior based on stated readiness to act: Development and validation of a prediction model</title>
      <link>/publication/green-et-al-2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/green-et-al-2021/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Social engagement early in the U.S. COVID-19 crisis: Exploring social support and prosocial behavior between those with and without depression or anxiety in an online sample</title>
      <link>/publication/mcguire-et-al-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/mcguire-et-al-2020/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cognitive restructuring vs. defusion: Impact on craving, healthy and unhealthy food intake</title>
      <link>/publication/karekla-et-al-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/karekla-et-al-2020/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Want to see more behavior? Consider institutional-level positive reinforcement</title>
      <link>/publication/kurz-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/kurz-2019/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note&lt;/em&gt;. In the original paper, I mistakenly forgot to include the focal article by Newsom and colleagues (2019) in the reference section. Though we eventually caught the mistake in the publishing process, I was told it was too late to correct the mistake. &lt;em&gt;Sigh&lt;/em&gt;. You can find their original article at &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jcbs.2018.11.005&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jcbs.2018.11.005&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How can process-based researchers bridge the gap between individuals and groups? Discover the dynamic p-technique</title>
      <link>/publication/kurz-et-al-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/kurz-et-al-2019/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Psychological inflexibility among Hispanic college students: Introducing the 6-item Acceptance and Action Questionnaire for Weight-related Difficulties</title>
      <link>/publication/flynn-et-al-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/flynn-et-al-2019/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Examining self-compassion in romantic relationships</title>
      <link>/publication/jacobson-et-al-2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/jacobson-et-al-2018/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A development assets approach in East Africa: Can Swahili measures capture adolescent competencies and ecological experiences?</title>
      <link>/publication/drescher-et-al-2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/drescher-et-al-2018/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How Bayesian estimation might improve CBS measure development: A case study with body-image flexibility in Hispanic students</title>
      <link>/publication/kurz-flynn-et-al-2016/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/kurz-flynn-et-al-2016/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Measuring social desirability across language and sex: A comparison of Marlowe–Crowne Social Desirability Scale factor structures in English and Mandarin Chinese in Malaysia</title>
      <link>/publication/kurz-drescher-et-al-2016/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 May 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/kurz-drescher-et-al-2016/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mediating the relation between workplace stressors and distress in ID support staff: Comparison between the roles of psychological inflexibility and coping styles</title>
      <link>/publication/kurz-et-al-2014/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/kurz-et-al-2014/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Warning:&lt;/strong&gt; In some regards, I&amp;rsquo;m proud of this paper. It is my first first-authored paper and the first paper for which I was the primary data analyst. Through this project, I got a great introduction to mediation, path analysis, and structural equation modeling. This was also my first experience where someone entrusted me with their data. The paper was accepted in my second year of grad school.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, in the years since then, I&amp;rsquo;ve learned a lot about longitudinal data analysis, multilevel thinking, and the distinction between between- and within-person processes. These studies have led me to conclude that cross-sectional data are a poorly-suited for studying person-level mediation. It&amp;rsquo;s not impossible that the mediational processes discussed and estimated in this paper are reasonable approximations of the day-to-day processes as lived in the lives of our participants and others like them. But it&amp;rsquo;s a stretch and I recommend others take the findings in this paper very lightly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you would like an introduction to the issues I&amp;rsquo;m dancing around, I recommend the (2012) chapter by the great Ellen Hamaker, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.guilford.com/books/Handbook-of-Research-Methods-for-Studying-Daily-Life/Mehl-Conner/9781462513055&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Why researchers should think &amp;ldquo;within-person&amp;rdquo;: A paradigmatic rationale&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. These opinions are mine and mine alone. I do not speak for my co-authors.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Smoking, nicotine dependence and motives to quit in Asian-American versus Caucasian college students</title>
      <link>/publication/bowen-kurz-2012b/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Oct 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/bowen-kurz-2012b/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Between-session practice and therapeutic alliance as predictors of mindfulness after mindfulness-based relapse prevention</title>
      <link>/publication/bowen-kurz-2012a/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Mar 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/bowen-kurz-2012a/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
